Okay, today's דף daf is נ"ז. Nun Zayin. We pick up at
the top of נ"ז. Nun Zayin. We are finishing up a משנה
mishna that spoke about you can have somebody testifying on three years
of חזקה, chazakah, each year independently to a different set of witnesses.
The גמרא Gemara had a whole discussion of דבר ולא חצי דבר
davar ve-lo chatzi davar
that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva wouldn't allow that, but the חכמים Chachamim
do because each year is independent. Why is each year independent? The
רשב"ם Rashbam said because what they're seeing everything they can see that
year. תוספות Tosafot went even further and he said no, it's because
actually one testimony of eating for one year has independent worth in
בית דין. Beis Din. If it's not going to be part of
a חזקה chazakah testimony, it'll be part of a testimony that the
person has to reimburse for the produce that they ate. So that
was the idea of three separate witness groups for three separate years.
And then the משנה mishna ended with a case of three brothers
ראובן שמעון ולוי. Reuven Shimon and Levi. ראובן Reuven testifies to year
one, שמעון Shimon to year two, לוי Levi to year three, and
then a third person מרדכי, Mordechai, let's call him, who will combine
with each, testify for all three years. So that's three separate testimonies
and that works, even though two brothers can't testify on the same
thing. But here each brother is testifying on a year that the
other brother is not, so that works. You had a question?
It's four people, right?
Four people, right. Three brothers and one other person, correct. Okay, so
ההוא שטרא דהוה חתימי ליה בי תרי. Hahu shtara de-hava chatimi lei
bei krei. Now with that in mind, let's read the following case
on the top of נ"ז עמוד א'. Nun Zayin Amud Aleph. ההוא
שטרא דהוה חתימי ליה בי תרי. Hahu shtara de-hava chatimi lei bei
krei. There's a certain document that two people were testified on it,
okay? We'll call them ראובן Reuven and מרדכי, Mordechai, okay? שכיב חד
מניהו. Shechiv chad minayhu. One of them passed away. אתא אחוה דהאי
דקאי. Asa achua de-hai de-kai. So מרדכי Mordechai passed away, so שמעון
Shimon came along, וחד אחרינא, ve-chad achrina, and some other stranger from
the street לאסהודי אחתימת ידא דאידך, le-as-hudi a-chatimat yada de-idach, to testify
on מרדכי's Mordechai signature. So you get it? ראובן Reuven here,
okay, here's the שטרא... shtara... okay, ראובן Reuven and מרדכי. Mordechai. Okay,
so here's מרדכי, Mordechai, he's dead, okay, he died. Here's ראובן. Reuven.
Okay, so ראובן Reuven is going to say that's my signature, and
that's good because a person can testify to their own signature. You
don't need two witnesses if you're testifying to your own signature. מרדכי
Mordechai obviously can't testify to his. We'll come along שמעון, Shimon, who
is ראובן's Reuven brother as we know, okay,
and maybe somebody else, ברק, Barak,
okay, and these two will testify to מרדכי's Mordechai signature. Alright? Okay,
that's what's going to happen. Now, okay, so אתא אחוה דהאי דקאי,
Asa achua de-hai
de-kai, the one that was, the brother of the guy that was
still alive came, וחד אחרינא, ve-chad achrina, and some other person לאסהודי
אחתימת ידא דאידך, le-as-hudi a-chatimat yada de-idach, to testify on the signature
of the guy that's dead because if you're not testifying on your
own signature, you need two witnesses to say yes, we recognize that
that's מרדכי's Mordechai signature. סבר רבינא למימר, Savar Ravina le-meimar, so רבינא
Ravina was of the opinion to say היינו מתניתין, Hainu matnisin, that's
our משנה, mishna, ג' אחין ואחד מצטרפין עמהם, Gimmel achin ve-echad mitztarfin
immahem, that can work, okay, because even though שמעון Shimon is ראובן's
Reuven brother, okay, but they're testifying on different things. He's testifying on
his signature, he together with this ברק Barak are testifying on that
signature. Now it's true they combine to testify on the whole שטרא.
shtara. Maybe you could say oh, can't combine because you're using שמעון
Shimon and ראובן Reuven together for the שטרא. shtara. But then but
look, our משנה mishna works. You had ראובן שמעון ולוי, Reuven Shimon
and Levi, each one testifying to a different year of חזקה, chazakah,
right? Remember that משנה, mishna, each one testifying to a different year
of חזקה chazakah and that worked, right? In our משנה's mishna case
was,
okay, ראובן Reuven said year one, שמעון Shimon said year two, לוי
Levi said year three, and the מרדכי Mordechai here testified on all
three years. Okay, so you basically had, right, מרדכי מרדכי מרדכי, Mordechai
Mordechai Mordechai,
okay, and that worked. So you don't say oh look, you know,
these are combining to be a testimony of חזקה. chazakah. Since each
year is independent, right, you can have brothers even though because that's
year one and there's no brother on year one, no brother on
year two, even though they combine. So here too, שמעון Shimon and
ברק Barak are testifying on מרדכי. Mordechai. They're all strangers to מרדכי.
Mordechai. That works, then they can combine with ראובן's Reuven testimony on
his own signature. Even though the combined effect is to validate the
שטרא, shtara, each testimony exists without a relative. Okay, so that's a
good comparison. So it says סבר רבינא למימר היינו מתניתין. Savar Ravina
le-meimar hainu matnisin. This is our משנה, mishna, ג' אחין ואחד מצטרפין
עמהם. Gimmel achin ve-echad mitztarfin immahem. אמר ליה רב אשי, Amar lei
Rav Ashi, so רב אשי Rav Ashi said מי דמי? Mi dami?
You can't compare it. התם לא נפיק מכדי ריבעא דממונא אפומא דחד.
Hatam lo nafik miche-dei riva de-mamona apuma de-chad.
In our, in the משנה, mishna, it's not true... the entire money
minus a quarter, which is another way of saying three quarters, three
quarters of the money is not being extracted on the basis of
one witness. הכא Hacha *Hacha* in our case, נפיק רבעא *nafik riv'a*...
I'm sorry, no, סליחה *selicha*, דאחי *de-achai*. On the basis of brothers.
הכא *Hacha* in our case, נפיק תלתא רבעי דממונא אפומא דאחי *nafik
tlata riv'ei demamona apuma de-achai*, three quarters of the money is being
extracted on the basis of brothers. What does that mean? It means
that at the end of the day in this case, okay, even
the point is look, view the brothers as, you know, the presumption
here of the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* or the analogy is, don't think
of brothers worse than if it was the same person because the
reason of brothers is that, you know, you're going to be have
a vested interest, or you're not going to be objective. Okay, so
the same way I'm two witnesses, right? First I'm going to testify
this and then I'm going to step over here and testify that,
right? I can't be two witnesses, I'm only one person. So two
brothers also can't be two witnesses. They're not better than one person,
two brothers. That's the assumption. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
okay, let's pretend ראובן, שמעון, ולוי *Reuven, Shimon, ve-Levi* were all one
person. Okay, so then you have ראובן ומרדכי *Reuven u-Mordechai* combining for
a חזקה chazakah *chazakah* of three years. Half of the testimony is
based on ראובן *Reuven*, ראובן *Reuven* and his brothers. Half of the
testimony is based on מרדכי *Mordechai*. That will work. The same way
ראובן, ראובן, וראובן *Reuven, Reuven, ve-Reuven* will work, ראובן, שמעון, ולוי *Reuven,
Shimon, ve-Levi* will work and in the end of the day, half
is being affected by this and half is being affected by this.
That works. Let's go look over here. In this case, if you
look at ראובן *Reuven* and שמעון *Shimon* as essentially one sort of
party, okay, half of the שטר *shtar* is being validated by ראובן
*Reuven*, and the other half of the שטר *shtar* is being validated
by ראובן *Reuven*'s brother, which is like, like ראובן *Reuven*, and ברק
*Barak*. So three quarters of the שטר *shtar* is being validated by
ראובן *Reuven*, ראובן *Reuven* and brothers. Okay, and that's not good. It
needs to be two witnesses equally weighted. Now, what this presupposes is
that let's forget שמעון *Shimon*. Let's assume can ראובן *Reuven* actually say,
'Whoa, I'm testifying on my own signature and I'm testifying on מרדכי
*Mordechai*'s together with the help of ברק *Barak*'? And the answer is
he cannot. For the same reason he is then validating three quarters
of the שטר *shtar*. So the same way ראובן *Reuven* cannot do
that, שמעון *Shimon* cannot do that either. But in this case, ראובן
*Reuven* who said three years and מרדכי *Mordechai* who said three years
would be fine. So therefore this is not good because three quarters
of the money is being extracted by ראובן *Reuven* plus his brothers.
Okay, and therefore it is not valid. Now, actually תוספות Tosafot, *Tosafot*
says there's actually a way you could, you could make this שטר
*shtar* valid. And here's the way you make this שטר *shtar* valid.
Okay, ראובן *Reuven* gets,
doesn't testify at all. שמעון, לוי, ברק *Shimon, Levi, Barak* testify, מרדכי
*Mordechai*. ראובן *Reuven* says, let's say I'm ראובן *Reuven*, okay, I'm going
to
go, I think I'll sign my signature just to see what it
looks like, and I sign my signature and I leave the piece
of paper there and I walk out of the room. Then you
two can come and testify, 'Hey, we saw ראובן *Reuven*'s signature and
that signature on the שטר *shtar* is just like his signature, we've
seen his signature'. Okay, so there is a way actually you could
do this, okay, by me making my signature available to other people
who will then recognize my signature and testify to it. But as
long as I am testifying, ראובן *Reuven* is testifying to this, he
cannot also testify on the other half of the שטר *shtar*. Yes.
In the ראובן *Reuven* game, so ראובן *Reuven* and שמעון *Shimon* can't
be the קרובים *krovim* on the שטר *shtar*. That's what you're saying?
Forget let's say this was ראובן *Reuven* and שמעון *Shimon* this time.
Well clearly they're brothers, they can't, right.
Even if the לוה *loveh* was okay with it?
Sure, you can't have brothers who are witnesses.
No, even if I sign and I am okay with ראובן *Reuven*
and שמעון *Shimon* being...
well, I mean, if you sign yourself, then you're הודה בעל דין
*hodeh ba'al din* and you don't need ראובן *Reuven* and שמעון *Shimon*.
So I'm trying to sort of think about the case where we
would have your own, you know what I'm saying? All right, okay,
so that was a nice little fun application of our משנה Mishnah
*mishnah* and this conceptual way of sort of seeing three brothers as,
you know, it would work if they would all work if they
were the same person. All right, so now, okay, so that was
the end of that משנה Mishnah. *mishnah*. Let's now look at the
next משנה Mishna, *mishnah*. אלו דברים שיש להם חזקה chazakah ואלו דברים
שאין להם חזקה chazakah *Elu devarim she-yesh lahem chazakah ve-elu devarim she-ein
lahem chazakah*. The following things, okay, now it doesn't mean things, it
means the following acts are types of חזקה chazakah *chazakah* that work
and the following are acts that types types of חזקה chazakah *chazakah*
that doesn't work. You know, that's a classic sort of structure of
the משנה Mishna. *mishnah*. Right? במה מדליקין ובמה אין מדליקין *Bameh madlikin
u-vameh ein madlikin*. You know, you know אלו דברים *elu devarim* this
and אלו דברים *elu devarim* that, שאין *she-ein* that. Now, the interestingly,
I would just say that the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* says that רבנו
חננאל *Rabbeinu Chananel* thinks that this is going on the חזקה chazakah
*chazakah* we just discussed. Meaning the חזקה chazakah *chazakah* not of three
years, but the חזקה chazakah *chazakah* of taking possession. He very vociferously
argues with that, and we're going to go with the רשב"ם Rashbam
*Rashbam*'s read. It seems very much reinforced by the facts and by
the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*. And the assumption here is that that discussion
about a חזקה chazakah *Chazakah* to transfer property property was a little
bit of a like of a of a what's it called of
a digression. You know, that was bracketed. We're back to the main
חזקה chazakah *Chazakah* of this פרק perek *Perek*, which is the חזקה
chazakah *Chazakah* of three years that's serving as evidence that I own
the property. And the following things work for that and the following
things do not. Okay, המעמיד בהמה בחצר *Ha'ma'amid Behemah Bechatzer*, I was
having my animals, like my chickens and my cows, and they were
in a חצר chatzer. *Chatzer*. Now, חצר chatzer. *Chatzer*, let's remember, is
not a שדה *Sadeh*. It's the courtyard, which is shared houses. Okay,
but you know, Eli and I both have houses in that courtyard.
Eli is either living in his house or he's somewhere a little
bit away. And while he's away, I am for three years having
my chickens and geese and cows and sheep all spend all like
use this חצר chatzer *Chatzer*. And he hasn't said one word. Alright?
So that is not going to The first list is let me
just tell you not a חזקה chazakah *Chazakah*. That is not going
to work because that's a sort of a temporary use. Okay, and
it's not seen, you know, like when I harvest the fruit of
the field, I am taking benefit that oh, that should be his,
that's just away from him, right? So this is seen as a
temporary use. He's not מקפיד makpid *Makpid*. He'll get rid of me
when he wants to use it. Or it's our shared Well, okay,
you're right. That's a good question. We're going to get to that
because שותפים *Shutafim* raises interesting questions. Okay, so let's hold that and
let's bracket that. But you know, but this case at least he
can say, as soon as he wants to use it, he'll kick
me off. It's not like I'm harvesting the wheat, you know, which
he's not going to get back. He doesn't have a need for
it, he lets me use it in the interim.
So you're claiming what you'd be claiming
He sold me the חצר chatzer. *Chatzer*.
Yeah, as opposed to you know, there's some חזקה chazakah *Chazakah* for
like doing things in the
Yeah, yeah, we're not dealing with those חזקות chazakos *Chazakot*. That's second
פרק perek. *Perek* חזקות *Chazakot*. We're not dealing with it. תנור וכיריים
*Tannur ve'chirayim*, let's say similarly I put an oven and a millstone
and a כיריים *Kirayim* which is back to a different type of
an oven, okay, which are all considered to be portable. So again,
I'm using the חצר chatzer *Chatzer*, but in no way that I've
sort of made any permanent changes where he could say, hey, I
let those use it until I needed it and then I would
kick him off. Alright. ומגדל תרנגולים *Umegadel tarnigolim*, and I could also
raise my chickens. Okay, I I already mentioned that.
ונותן זבלו *Venoten zivlo*
זבל *Zevel*
ונותן זבלו בחצר *Venoten zivlo bechatzer*. And also, I can Now if
I'm actually what do you call it? If I'm actually
fertilizing the חצר chatzer *Chatzer*, Eli's very happy. But I'm not fertilizing
it. I'm just storing my my manure there. Okay. But again, that's
seen as, you know, the way we feel like ugh, wouldn't that
do some damage? But apparently that was, you know, not seen as
a problem. It wouldn't do any permanent change and he's going to
let me use it. So any type of these temporary uses where
he can kick me off anytime he wants to use it, okay,
that is not a חזקה chazakah *Chazakah*. אין חזקה chazakah *Ein chazakah*.
That's not a חזקה chazakah *Chazakah*. אבל *Aval*, but if I were
actually to make some type of a structural change, עשה מחיצה m'chitzah
לבהמתו *Asah mechitza le'vehemto*. Now if I just made a מחיצה *Mechitza*,
Eli would say, oh thank you very much for making a מחיצה
*Mechitza* in my yard, get out of here now. Okay, so why
does he care that I'm making actual capital improvements on his property?
But I made a מחיצה *Mechitza* for the purpose of penning my
animals. So what I'm doing is I'm not just temporarily using my
animals, I am turning it into like an animal a barn. I'm
turning it into an animal pen. And that is seen as like
nobody would allow somebody to make that type of an ownership type
of a claim on their yard. They're not just using it without
me protesting. They're actually changing it. They're taking possession of it. They're
making it into this animal pen. Okay. גבוה עשרה טפחים tefachim, *Gavo'ah
asarah tefachim*, if it's of substance, ten טפחים tefachim, *Tefachim* high. וכן
לתנור וכיריים ורחיים *V'chen l'tannur v'chirayim v'rechayim*, or I made a fence
around it to make it a sort of a outdoor kitchen type
of a thing, you know? So it wasn't just that I was
using it, I was defining it as a as a different type
of a space. Alright? וכן לרחיים *V'chen l'rechayim*, or for the millstone.
הכניס תרנגולים לתוך הבית
*Hichnis tarnigolim le'toch habayit*. Now let's say I actually brought the chickens
into the house. Okay, now I didn't make a new structure, but
that is somehow seen also as not just like you're using it
and then get rid of the chickens, no harm no foul. Ha
ha, I just occurred to me that one. Okay, anyway, alright, that
was a good one, right Rabbi? Anyway,
but but if I bring it into the house, presumably even then
chickens in the house was not a normal thing, okay? It would
stink up the place, it would be seen as some type of
a change to the house. Like an easier or a
harder version even just?
Well, that's a good question. Some of this stuff you might imagine
might be right away. The משנה Mishna *Mishna*, let's take a look
at the משנה Mishna *Mishna*, okay?
I tell you, that's a very poultry example.
Oh,
okay. לתוך הבית ועשה מקום לזבלו *Le'toch habayit ve'asah makom le'zivlo*, or
you made a similarly, you know, like you didn't just you didn't
just pile your manure there, you designated a made a space, presumably
you surrounded it with some type of a
מחיצה *Mechitza*. it three טפחים tefachim high. Okay, this would only have
to be three טפחים, so it's not that there's this magic in
ten טפחים, it depends on the context and this context three טפחים
is significant enough. הרי זו חזקה, Harei zo chazakah, that works. Okay,
and again, you know, the point is that right, you might think
some of this is such a provocation maybe immediately, okay, but the
presumption here is that we're talking about three years. Let's take a
look now at the גמרא.
Gemara
מאי שנא רישא ומאי שנא סיפא?
Mai
shena reisha u-mai shena seifa?
let's check, this could be something else.
Yeah, yeah, I mean, obviously these are concrete examples and then you
can sort of like try to interpolate or extrapolate.
But let's say you took your pet in the house.
Yes, so presumably that would be different. Okay, מאי שנא רישא ומאי
שנא סיפא? Mai shena reisha u-mai shena seifa? What... in his house,
right, in his house. Right, what is...
they didn't have pets.
They didn't have pets. מאי שנא רישא ומאי שנא סיפא? Mai shena
reisha u-mai shena seifa? What is the difference between a... the way
the רשב"ם Rashbam explains it, your animal in the courtyard without a
wall around it and your animal in the courtyard with a wall
around it? So אמר עולא כל שאילו בנכסי הגר קנה בנכסי חבירו
קנה. Amar Ula kol she-ilu be-nichsei ha-ger kanah be-nichsei chaveiro kanah. Anything
that would work by הפקר, hefker, now that is a way of
telling you we know we're talking about the חזקה Chazaka of taking
possession because you don't need a חזקה Chazaka of three years against
the נכסי הגר. nichsei ha-ger. So the phrase of
נכסי הגר, nichsei ha-ger, a גר ger who died and therefore the
property is ownerless, means a חזקה Chazaka of taking possession. So anything
that works, a type of a חזקה Chazaka that works to take
possession
works for נכסי חבירו. nichsei chaveiro. Now, I'll just point out parenthetically,
רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel would say we're talking about two types of
חזקות of taking possession: taking possession from הפקר, hefker, taking possession from
a sale. Okay, but the רשב"ם Rashbam again, and we're going to
read it his way, says no, no, נכסי חבירו nichsei chaveiro here
means against your friend, not that he's willingly transferring it. The חזקה
chazaka of evidence that I bought it, the חזקה chazaka of three
years. So anything that works for a חזקה chazakah? of possession works
for a חזקה chazakah. of three years. Now, until now for the
last week, I've been telling you that there's a basic difference, which
don't worry, the גמרא's Gemara going to point out, I didn't make
it up. Okay, I've been telling you the basic difference is that
a חזקה chazakah of taking possession is that you benefit the property,
a חזקה chazakah of three years is that you take benefit from
the property. But this claim is actually claiming that they're fundamentally the
same. Okay, which is going to be immediately rejected.
כל שאילו בנכסי הגר קנה, Kol she-ilu be-nichsei ha-ger kanah, anything that
would work by taking... a חזקה chazakah. of taking possession, בנכסי חבירו
קנה, be-nichsei chaveiro kanah, works as a חזקה chazaka. for proving you
own it. כל שאילו בנכסי הגר לא קנה, Kol she-ilu be-nichsei ha-ger
lo kanah, anything that does not work for taking possession, בנכסי חבירו
לא קנה, be-nichsei chaveiro lo kanah, doesn't work. So presumably the argument
is building a fence, you could understand what attracted עולא Ula to
that explanation because the classic חזקה chazaka of taking possession is נעל
גדר ופרץ. na'al gader u-faratz. So building a fence is improving the
property and that works for the three years, whereas just using it
doesn't work for the three years. So that's the distinction. In the
beginning you're just using it and in the end you're making some
improvement to the property and at least within the משנה Mishna that
exactly tracks the difference between a חזקה chazaka. of taking possession. A
חזקה chazaka. of taking possession only works when you're making an improvement
in the property which we could say happens at the end of
the משנה. Mishna, Of course, chickens in the house is not exactly
clear, but some of those cases, building the fences are real improvements
to the property. So מתקיף לה רב ששת, Maskif lah Rav Sheshes,
or רב ששת Rav Sheshes challenges, וכללא הוא? Ve-chlala hu? Is this
really a rule? I'm going to show you this rule doesn't work
at all. והרי ניר, Ve-harei nir, how about, you know, plowing a
land and not actually planting it? What's that called?
Laying it fallow.
Not laying it fallow, it's different. It's you actually turn over the
soil. Okay, ניר Nir is a turning over of the soil without
planting. So anyway, that's what ניר nir is. Okay? דבנכסי הגר קנה,
De-ve-nichsei ha-ger kanah, if it was נכסי הגר nichsei ha-ger it would
work because you've improved the land. בנכסי חבירו לא קנה. Be-nichsei chaveiro
lo kanah. We had that discussion way at the beginning of the
פרק if you remember, that doesn't work. I've improved your land, I
haven't taken anything from it. You're very happy, I'm going to let
him do as much as he wants and then I'll kick him
off. Okay? So clearly that doesn't work. By גר ger it's about
improving, by חזקה chazaka. of three years it's about taking benefit. Okay?
והרי אכילת פירות, Ve-harei achilas peiros, or the flip, taking... harvesting the
produce. בנכסי חבירו קנה, Be-nichsei chaveiro kanah, that works to prove three
years because that's exactly classic three years. I've been harvesting the produce
for three years. I've been taking the benefit that should have been
yours and that's my proof. בנכסי הגר לא קנה, Be-nichsei ha-ger lo
kanah, but in נכסי הגר nichsei ha-ger it doesn't work because you
didn't improve the property. Okay? So this like... this is exactly what
I've been telling you for all along. So here it's very nice,
I mean, to abstract it the way I did, giving benefit or
taking benefit, but it's basically saying these are fundamentally the same. Now
it's not saying that there are never overlaps, right? There could be
a case like bringing the animals in and building a fence, which
is a combination of improving the property and tak... taking benefit; so
there are areas of overlap, but that doesn't explain the משנה, Mishna:
you can't say the חזקה chazaka. of three years follows the חזקה
chazaka. taking possession. That is not פשט Pshat in the משנה. Mishna
חזקה of three years is fundamentally about taking benefit. So once that's
true, what's the difference of the beginning of the משנה Mishnah where
you're taking benefit and the end of the משנה Mishnah you're taking
benefit? In both cases, you're taking benefit. אלא אמר רב נחמן אמר
רבה בר אבוה, Ella amar Rav Nachman amar Rabba bar Avuha, rather
says רב נחמן Rav Nachman in the name of רבה בר
אבוה, Rabba bar Avuha, הכא—so here's where I gave it away too
soon—בחצר השותפין עסקינן. be'chatzer ha'shutfim askinan. We're not talking about סתם, stam,
you know, you know, I walk into Eli's front yard like we
all have our own different front yards and I walk into his
front yard and start storing and keeping my, you know, storing all
of my—Eli's away on vacation—and I store all of my junk in
his front yard. Okay, that's what we initially thought. I have my
chickens in his yard. Okay, so we have separate front yards and
then I'm going to claim it's my front yard, he sold the
yard to me. No, no, no. We're not talking about that. We're
talking about we start with a joint courtyard, which is the classic
case in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, we have two houses, they open
up into a shared courtyard. And what I am claiming is that
he sold me his portion in the courtyard. And therefore, certain types
of usages like we're going to assume a normal stranger would be
upset if you had your chickens in his yard. Okay, and that
could be a חזקה right away. But if it's a shared courtyard,
certain type of usages he won't be upset about; others he will.
Okay, so הכא בחצר השותפין עסקינן, hacha be'chatzer ha'shutfim askinan, דבהעמדה כדי
לא קפדי. de'be'ha'amada kidei lo kapdi. If it's just about, you know,
simply using it even though maybe it's a type of usages that
we don't do—normally in courtyards we don't keep chickens in the courtyard,
we keep them, you know, somewhere else—okay, but nevertheless we own it
jointly so we can assume he'll let that go, okay? But אמחיצה
קפדי, a'mechitzah kapdi,
but to actually make some type of a structural change, he would
say something about that. So the reason we shift it to חצר
השותפין chatzer ha'shutfim is because we're assuming that if it's a normal
stranger that I'm using their yard and putting my chickens there, okay,
that actually would be enough of a provocation. Even if it's true
you could kick me off at any point, still, like you don't
like a stranger to put stuff in your yard, okay? So therefore,
we can't—we in order to make sense of the משנה mishna. why
the first case is not a provocation, we have to say we're
talking about a shared courtyard. If it's a shared courtyard, so certain
types of things I let go even though normally you're not supposed
to do it, okay? But other types of things, you know, more
permanent change, that's something I'm going to put my foot down about.
Now תוספות, by the way, parenthetically, you might be remembering there's a
whole discussion earlier whether שותפין shutfim can have a חזקה against one
another. Okay, but the short answer is there are times that they
can. When it's something that is seen as enough of a provocation
and something that even a שותף shutaf would not let go without
saying something, a שותף shutaf can sometimes have a חזקה against another.
And this takes three years or not?
Yeah, three years. All this assumes three years.
Okay, so even though we never said that?
Yeah, but that's sort of, at least the רשב"ם Rashbam is taking
that for granted. Okay, so that's the basic answer. We're dealing with
a shared yard and therefore smaller things are not a provocation, bigger
things are. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: ובהעמדה כדי
לא קפדי? U'be'ha'amada kidei lo kapdi? Are you telling me that partners
who share a courtyard are not—do not like object, you know, have
a basis for objection when you use it, you know, in some
type of a way that you're putting things, storing things there which
I guess are not implicitly the normal use of the yard?
והתנן, Ve'hatnan, like it's just the first half of the משנה, you're
telling me therefore he would let it go? והתנן, Ve'hatnan, but we
taught in the משנה: השותפין שנדרו הנאה זה מזה. ha'shutfim she'nadru hana'ah
zeh mi'zeh. So Eli and I share a courtyard and we're in
a fight. It's a good thing we don't have נדרים nedarim anymore,
you know, because like when couples get into fights, you know, they
cool off and then the next day they make up. You know,
in time of the משנה they would have to go do התרת
נדרים hatarat nedarim because in the middle of the fight they're making
a נדר. neder. I'm making a נדר neder all of my possessions
are forbidden to you. He says, oh yeah, you can't do that
to me, I make a נדר neder all my possessions are forbidden
to you. So we do that to each other right while we
are fighting about this courtyard because we're getting really angry. We have
this shared courtyard. So now this is jointly owned. How can we
use the courtyard? Because by using the courtyard, I'm also using my
possession and his and I'm benefiting from his possession. השותפין שנדרו הנאה
זה מזה, אסורין ליכנס
לחצר. ha'shutfim she'nadru hana'ah zeh mi'zeh, asurin lihaness le'chatzer. They can't enter
into a joint חצר. chatzer, And that shows you—now the assumption here
is that any type of a use that a normal person wouldn't
be מקפיד makpid on is not considered הנאה. hana'ah. Now thankfully we're
not learning נדרים Nedarim right now so I don't have to fully
defend that position, okay? But you know, it could be there's real
benefit, I get real benefit from going through the yard and whatever,
but if it's a type of a use that you don't care,
you let anybody do it, so
it's not
really—it could be conceptually we're saying it's not even worth the— שוה
פרוטה shava pruta or maybe what we're more saying is I'm not
being נהנה neheneh from you. It's not like you gave me something.
If you're willing to let anybody do it, right, I didn't get
any you didn't do me any favor, and you know, there's nothing
I particularly you gave to me. It's something that you generally waive
and allow anyone to do. So we'll just accept that for now,
that if it's a הנאה hana'ah that you're not מקפיד makpid on,
it's not considered a problem in a case of a נדר. neder.
So it says therefore, but nevertheless we can't use one another's חצר.
So it shows that the use of a חצר is normally something
that you're מקפיד makpid on. So if that's normally something you're מקפיד
makpid on, why doesn't it work for a חזקה? Now there's also
a little bit of a problem because, you know, in one case
it's even I mean you could say it's a קל וחומר kal
v'chomer question, you know, it's even walking through the yard is considered
to be a problem, right, whereas in the other case it's like
you know the problem is using it in ways that it would
normally be used to put chickens there, right, so obviously they're not
you know exactly the same, but anyway, but that's the question. You
see there's some basic הקפדה hakpadah that goes on here
and therefore and maybe even though it's true we use we generally
use the courtyard together because that's assumed like you're allowing me to
do it, so you have at least a basis to be מקפיד
makpid and if you have a basis to be מקפיד makpid and
that's why it's a problem for a נדר neder because you normally
would have a right to object, then the question is and therefore
why doesn't it work for חזקה. So the גמרא gemara lest that's
the question so let's see what the answer is. אלא אמר רב
נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה הכא ברחבה שלאחורי הבתים עסקינן. Ela amar
Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha hacha b'rachavah she'l'achorei habatim askinan. Okay,
you're right, we're not talking about the courtyard, the courtyard is things
people generally are מקפיד makpid on and maybe it would be a
חזקה just if you have adverse use even in a case of
a joint courtyard. What we're talking even if it's only like not
a permanent use. What we're talking about is your backyard, your alley
behind the houses, okay. So the alley behind the houses, you know,
people put their garbage there, whatever, you're not so מקפיד makpid what
other people are doing in a חצר. It's an alley, I know,
the משנה what can I tell you. דבמדי לא קפדי D'bamadei lo
kapdi that there we could say that something that normal people aren't
מקפיד makpid if it's just a temporary use, okay, מחיצה קפדי, m'chitzah
kapdi, but on a מחיצה it is and maybe according to this
answer we don't have to be talking about שותפין, shutfin, right, maybe
it's like a back alley, back alley people generally don't care as
much, it's not your front yard. Okay, but Michael correctly says the
משנה says חצר not רחבה rachavah but what are you going to
do.
Okay,
רב פפא אמר אידי ואידי
Rav Pappa
amar idi
v'idi to a point basically.
Yeah, exactly, you're not מקפיד makpid for temporary use but to take
possession of it like to make a structural change. רב פפא אמר
אידי ואידי. Rav Pappa amar idi v'idi. No, no, let's go back
to the שותפין shutfin assumption, that was a good explanation. Because you
know logically it makes sense, right, your neigh- you know your you
know one of the tenants of the yard allows tolerates a certain
degree but not beyond you know but not a greater degree of
type of use. That makes sense. So all we have to do
it made internal sense we just have to make it work with
this discussion about a נדר. neder. So let's see how we're going
to do it. אידי ואידי בחצר השותפין. Idi v'idi b'chatzer shutfin. No,
no, we're talking back with the חצר owned by partners.
ואיכא דקפדי ואיכא דלא קפדי. Ve'ika d'kapdi ve'ika d'lo kapdi. And some
people are very מקפיד makpid on even small usages that they shouldn't
be doing and other people are not מקפיד makpid and other people
only when it gets to a certain level. גבי ממונא לקולא גבי
איסורא לחומרא. Gabi mamona l'kulah gabi issura l'chumra. By monetary issues we're
lenient and by by איסור issur by נדר neder we're strict. Now
what it means that by נדר neder we're strict makes sense. I
shouldn't use this courtyard when Eli and I took these vows against
one another because maybe Eli is generally מקפיד makpid and then I
would be violating the vow, I'd be getting benefit from him on
something he normally is מקפיד makpid that other people shouldn't use. So
that makes sense, we have to assume the worst case that he
is מקפיד makpid, and I shouldn't use it. But what do we
mean we're lenient by money? If lenient means I'm going to have
used it and then it's not going to be a חזקה because
it wasn't a permanent use. So what do you mean lenient? It's
lenient to Eli, it's not lenient to me, right? I mean there's
you know any that's the point about ממון, mamon, ממון mamon you
can't say מחמיר machmir or מיקל, meikel, anytime you're lenient for one
guy you're being strict for the guy who's opposing him. So what
we mean by lenient the רשב"ם Rashbam says is we mean let's
say לכתחילה l'chatchilah I were to come to בית דין beis din
and say the following question: can I use this courtyard that I
share with Eli? He's not around, I want to ask the Rabbi:
can I use this courtyard that I share with Eli to put
my chickens in there, okay? So the answer might have been: yeah,
we'll assume that Eli is not מקפיד, makpid some people are some
people are not, we'll assume he's not מקפיד makpid and we'll let
you use it. Okay, so since we would have let me use
it, we would have maybe the assumption, I'm already a part owner
of the yard, right, it's not like I'm a total stranger, I'm
not like I'm invading somebody's property. So we're going to assume that
he was of the people that aren't מקפיד makpid, and we would
let me, so if we're going to assume that he would let
me and I'm going to use it then it can't serve as
the basis for a חזקה. חזקה. Right? The basis of a חזקה
is the assumption that it was an adverse possession. So if it's
the type of thing that we would let me use because we
would assume he wouldn't be מקפיד, makpid, then it cannot serve as
the basis for a חזקה. Said another way, the way the רשב"ם
Rashbam says it is, let's drop the חומרא chumra and קולא kula
framing. Said another way the רשב"ם rashbam is Eli comes and says,
Dov, what have you been doing on there for three years? I
said, Yeah, you sold it to me. He says, I didn't sell
it to you, I just wasn't מקפיד, makpid. you know? So then
I am trying to prove that it's mine by my possession. I
can't prove it if it's a reasonable interpretation of the facts. Eli
was the original owner, he's the one that's מוחזק muchzak and an
original and a reasonable interpretation is that he's of the people that
aren't מקפיד. makpid, So because it's not evidently something that would lead
to somebody objecting, it's not a strong enough possession to cause a
חזקה. So it's what we sort of assumed all along. Temporary use
is a type of a thing rather than saying nobody is מקפיד,
makpid. it's a type of a thing where it's quite possible somebody
isn't מקפיד. makpid, Since it's quite possible this temporary use somebody isn't
מקפיד, makpid it's not the basis of a חזקה. I can't prove
that this shows that I bought it. But on the other hand,
since there's a possibility somebody is מקפיד makpid in the case of
נדר, neder, I'm not allowed to use it.
Yeah. I don't understand how someone's not מקפיד makpid right away by
putting your chickens in their house.
This is still
שותפין. shutfin.
Okay. Even so, but I thought it's שותפין shutfin for the חצר,
not for the house.
Yeah, so we never get back around to the house. We would
have to assume something similar to the house that we owned the
house בשותפות beshutafus and I'm claiming that he sold the whole house
to me. Okay, but by the way, the house actually, what do
you mean? The house actually it works for the chickens in the
house.
Could be right away.
Oh, right away. That I don't know. Okay, let's go. So anyway,
that's a nice answer in the גמרא. gemara? Let's keep on going.
רבינא אמר, Ravina amar, we're going to give yet another answer. רבינא
Ravina says
לעולם לא קפדי. leolam lo kapdi.
People aren't מקפיד makpid. as a rule. It's not that we have
to assume that there's a percentage that is מקפיד. makpid Nobody is
מקפיד makpid by partners at least in a courtyard. You want to
sometimes use your chickens, be my put them in the courtyard, be
my guest. Okay? So people aren't מקפיד makpid and therefore clearly not
מקפיד makpid and it's not a חזקה. Why is it a problem
by a נדר? neder? Because הא מני רבי אליעזר, ha mani Rabbi
Eliezer, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer he, our case by נדר neder where
it's no good is the position of רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says any benefit even a benefit people aren't מקפיד
makpid? on is a problem by נדרים. nedarim. Right? You heard that
I had a hard time explaining. So what, you're not מקפיד? makpid.
I'm still getting benefit from you. So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says
you're right, it doesn't matter if he's not מקפיד. makpid. You get
benefit from somebody, that's a problem with a
נדר. neder. דתניא detanya we taught in a ברייתא, braita, רבי אליעזר
אומר אפילו ויתור אסור במודר הנאה. Rabbi Eliezer omer afilu vitor assur
bemuder hana-a. Even something that people would like waive and not care
about, you know, is a problem by a case of מודר הנאה.
muder hana-a. So the example the רשב"ם Rashbam gives is, let's say
every time you buy a dozen eggs, I'm a storekeeper, I throw
in an extra egg. Okay? I just do that for all my
customers. Now you're מודר הנאה muder hana-a from me. You come and
buy the eggs. That's not a problem of הנאה hana-a because you're
actually it's an equal transaction. Okay? But I throw in an extra
egg for you just like I do for everybody else. That's a
problem according to רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. According to the חכמים chachamim
it's not. It's something you willingly give everybody, it's like you're not
מקפיד. makpid It's not a problem. But he says I don't care
if you willingly give it to everybody. You are getting a benefit,
you know, this other person is getting a benefit from him. So
even if it's a benefit he gives every person, it's a benefit
that's being received and therefore it's a problem by מודר הנאה. muder
hana-a. So even things people aren't מקפיד makpid on is a problem.
So now we can have that it's אסור assur by הנאה hana-a
and it's still a considered to be not מקפיד makpid and therefore
not a basis of חזקה. All right. So
that was the end of explaining that משנה. Okay, yes.
Is that like the central approach to נדרים nedarim or are these
just two approach like my intuition is like,
yeah, my intuition is רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer makes sense. You have
to defend the position that not מקפיד makpid? is not a problem.
I'm totally with you. Okay, but you know, but רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer is seen as the exception because he's the minority voice. But
logically רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would be the first thing you would
say. Who cares if the guy isn't מקפיד? You said you're not
going to get any הנאה hana-a from him and you got הנאה
hana-a from him. Okay, now the גמרא gemara says like this, אמר
רב יוחנן משום רבנא, Amar Rav Yochanan mishum Rabbana, וכל שותפין מעכבין
זה את זה חוץ מן הכביסה. vechol shutfin meakvin zeh es zeh
chutz min hakvisa. I can, we jointly own
a courtyard. Okay? We can I can stop you from making usage
of this courtyard in all matters. Now again, I assume it means
all matters except like the standard. If the standard is everybody takes
their lawn chair out in the courtyard and you know uses it
to read and to whatever and to you know and to sun
themself, you know, unless it means that everybody we're going back to
stuff of the first פרק. You know, the first you know like
can we as a corporation, you know, all of the tenants of
the courtyard can get together and say we're not going to allow
certain usages. Maybe. Sure. You all jointly own it. You could make
your rules about what you're allowed to use it for or not.
Okay, so the members of the courtyard can object to any type
of non-standard use or maybe they can make the rules as to
what are allowed usages and what are not allowed usages in the
courtyard. Anybody who's part of a co-op understands what we're talking about,
right? Do you get to make the rules about what are allowed
or not allowed חוץ מן הכביסה. chutz min hakevisah. The one thing
they cannot allow, they cannot prevent is people who want to do
their laundry in the courtyard. Why not? We're going to go do
your laundry somewhere else. Go do it by the river. No, because
שאין דרכן של בנות ישראל להתבזות על הכביסה, she'ein darkan shel bnot
yisrael lehitbazot al hakevisah,
because it's assumed that the women are going to do the laundry
and if they're going to do the laundry they're going to go
to the river and they might like lift up their skirts and
it would be considered not צניעות tzniut and therefore that's something that
you want to allow them to do in semi-privacy. You don't want
to force them to have to do in public. Okay and therefore
since it requires more exposing of yourself than would be normal, you
have no right to prevent them from doing it in the semi-privacy
of the courtyard.
Yes, I do think it's likely that this was a standard that
בנות ישראל bnot yisrael set for
themselves to say שאין דרכן. she'ein darkan. Right, they do not want,
their way is not to,
that's a good point. It's not like the rabbis are saying we
don't want to allow or we want to protect them from this.
I mean right, they have already decided that this is the standard
they want to maintain and we are helping them protect their own
standard. Right, that's a very nice point. I mean correct.
Yes, we
are going to make this rule to allow them to protect a
standard that they have accepted for themselves. Thank you, that's a good
point. Okay, so this allows us now, do you want to say
something?
Okay, so doing the laundry, not the laundry itself?
Not showing their clothes? I think so. I
think שהרשב"ם אומר שצריכות לעמוד שם יחפות לגלות שוק לעמוד בנהר. sheharashbam
omer shetzrichot la'amod sham yechefot legalot shok la'amod banahar.
What? שוק shok is שוק? shok? שוק? shok? Oh שוק. shok. Yeah,
the שוק shok is not the thigh, the שוק shok is the
calf. Okay,
so basically yes, because if you go into the river you have
to like lift up, you don't want to get your clothes... yeah,
that's the way it's generally understood. Okay, because we'll see in a
minute, because the next גמרא gemara as well. So now we digress
a little. ועוצם עיניו מראות ברע. veotzem einav meirot bera. So this
is praising the person who closes his eyes from seeing something evil.
So this is going to be interpreted as a man closing his
eyes so as not to be sort of sexually provoked by
seeing women in a way that would normally not be exposed. So
אמר רבי חייא בר אבא זה שנסתכל בנשים בשעה שעומדות על הכביסה.
amar rabbi chiya bar abba zeh shenistakel benashim besha'ah she'omdot al hakevisah.
So here you go, right, it's specifically about looking at the women.
Right, so not, this is a person who walks by the river
and there are the women doing their laundry and he makes a
point, a man not a person, a man, and he makes a
point of not looking. Okay, so that shows that that's something that
you want to protect people's privacy in terms of that. So היכי
דמי, heichi dami, what's the case says the גמרא? Gemara אי דאיכא
דרכא אחרינא, ei de'ika darcha achrina, if there was another way to
get to where you were going, רשע, rasha, what do you mean,
don't praise him that he's not looking. He shouldn't even be tempting
himself. He should be going in a completely different way. Okay, so
you don't get any compliments for closing your eyes if you shouldn't
have been going that way in the first place. אי דליכא דרכא
אחרינא, ei deleika darcha achrina, if he has no other choice, this
is the only path. Now one wonders what it means איכא ika
or ליכא. leika. Let's say this saves him a half hour. Okay,
but whatever, if this is the only reasonable
path, so אנוס הוא, anus hu, so somebody who doesn't close his
eyes, he didn't do the right thing? I mean what are you
supposed to do? You have to get from point A to point
B. You're supposed to walk with your eyes closed? So why you
have to, so you understand why you're praising this guy, but it
makes it sound like somebody who doesn't do this is doing something
not ideal. You know, what's a normal person supposed to do? Normal
man supposed to do? So the גמרא Gemara says no, לעולם דאיכא
דרכא אחרינא. le'olam de'ika darcha achrina. There was another way, so... ואפילו
הכי דליכא excuse me, דליכא דרכא אחרינא, there was no other way.
ואפילו הכי מיבעי ליה למינס נפשיה. veafilu hachi mibaye leh lemeinas nafshih.
And nevertheless, even it's not you're not a total אנוס, anus, you
could go ahead and like exert a little extra effort if you
want to read the way the רשב"ם Rashbam says להטות עיניו לצד
אחר. lehatot einav letzad acher. So דהיינו דמשתבח ביה קרא דאנס נפשיה
חסיד הוא. dehaynu demishtabach beh kera de'anas nafshih chasid hu. So yeah,
this was your only way, but you can do it in a
way that avoids looking and in
a way that doesn't avoid looking. Maybe it's a little harder to
avoid looking, you might trip or something or it really takes extra
effort, but that's why it's praiseworthy. Okay, so there you go, so
this becomes again an interesting גמרא Gemara. that fits into a range
of גמרות gemarot that are
about men looking at women and having sexual thoughts. Although I do
want to say that I think that's an interesting point that normally
the emphasis of those גמרות gemarot are on... a concern for a
man's illicit sexual thought. And that doesn't really is not really at
the forefront here. Here the forefront is is that's an invasion of
the privacy or, you know, אליץ פזות Alitz Pazot like the women
don't want to be looked at that way, right? It's not considered,
so there's a different emphasis here than the man's sexual thoughts, although
we still have the issue that it's describing it as רע, ra,
you know, so that's still obviously an issue. Okay, but there is
you there is at least that different emphasis. Yes.
It's not saying, oh, the women shouldn't be doing their laundry.
Oh right, that's good, it's the man's responsibility. Yes, that's an excellent
point as well, right? Which is a point I've made also in
other contexts, like that all of the emphases around like צניעות Tzniut
in the גמרא Gemara are really all primarily all about how the
way, right, men are looking at women and not about like, you
know, women having to cover themselves up. So that's also a very
good point, שקויח. Shkoiach. Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: בעי מיניה ר' יוחנן מרבי בנאה. Ba'ei minei Rabi Yochanan me'Rabi
Bana'ah. So now because that was a statement in the name of
רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan in the name of רבי בנאה, Rabi Bana'ah,
so we're going to now really digress even a little further and
have some statements of רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan with רבי בנאה. Rabi
Bana'ah. רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan asked רבי בנאה: Rabi Bana'ah: חלוק של
תלמיד חכם כיצד? Chaluk shel talmid chacham keitzad? What is, you know,
the shirt of or the cloak of a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham
supposed to look like? Says, so this is going to also tie
into this like צניעות Tzniut theme, but what's nice here is that
it's צניעות Tzniut about men. Okay, so it says: כל שאין בשרו
נראה מתחתיו. Kol she'ein besaro nir'eh mitachtav. The cloak, it's like a
cloak, it goes down to, you know, the bottom, it's not just
a—what do they call it? I guess a cloak, a toga or
something, a robe, well but it's—it's not an outer garment, it's an—it's
like against his flesh, a tunic, thank you, a tunic. And basically
it goes all the way down to his feet. You can't see
any skin from it. So here the concern is about men, not
about women, at least about a תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. So okay,
טלית של תלמיד חכם כיצד? Talit shel talmid chacham keitzad? How about
an outer garment, what's that supposed to—what's that look like that would
be a כבוד kavod way, you know, a dignified way of presenting
oneself? So he says: כל שאין חלוקו נראה מתחתיו טפח. Kol she'ein
chaluko nir'eh mitachtav tefach.
So that it totally covers up your tunic. So it's also—it doesn't
have to be literally get to the floor, you can have like
a—half of an inch or two inches, whatever, it could be a
little bit of your tunic appears outside, but it should be totally—but
it should be almost completely covering up, you know, almost full body
length. Okay, שולחן של תלמיד חכם כיצד? Shulchan shel talmid chacham keitzad?
How about a table of a תלמיד חכם? talmid chacham? What should
that look like?
שני שלישי גדיל ושליש גילוי. Shnei shlishi gadil u'shlish gilui. Two-thirds like
woven and one-third exposed. So what does this mean? So the רשב"ם
Rashbam says that what it means is, you know, actually some people,
we just got like this new wood table and we were told
we should not have a tablecloth on it, but do a runner.
But it's very like unusual for us, like to put the dishes
straight on the table. But you know, that's sometimes what people have,
they don't have,
you know, they don't have the whole table covered, they have a
runner down the middle and they have the dishes on the table
itself.
And the table—is the table better?
No, it looks better because you can see the nice table if
you only have a runner down the middle. So anyway, so the
רשב"ם says that's what we're talking about, that you do two-thirds of
the table, right, which is the cloth, and then the final third
here where people are putting down their plates, that's exposed, and that's
where they put down their plates. Okay, now why is that supposed
to be considered to be nice? He says,
let me see, ושליש חיצוני מגולה להניח עליו קערות וכוסות שלא יתלכלכו
המפה ויסבאו האוכלים. u'shlish chitzoni meguleh lehani'ach alav kearot ve'kosot she'lo yitlachlechu
ha'mapah ve'yasbu ha'ochlim.
So he says that way that you don't get the nice cloth
dirty, because you have your plates on the table itself. I guess
you're not worried about getting the table dirty. Okay, so the cloth
is where you lay out maybe the food or whatever, but people
are eating on the exposed part. Okay, that's one explanation. The other
explanation is that the—that the cloths are at the end and the
exposed part is in the middle. And then actually I guess people
would be, you know, eating on, you know, so the—a third at
the edges of each edge is where the cloth is and the
exposed third is in the middle. I'm not sure why that's supposed
to be nice. Okay.
Well, yeah, I guess that you then have
the—the—where you're eating is protected by the—by the cloth. Okay.
So, is
there a contrast between the women
exposed and the men totally covered? Oh, that's interesting.
And then the table's partly exposed and partly covered.
Oh, maybe it's like a euphemism for something.
Oh, like right, like for sex or something like that? Because right,
that's a good point. Maybe it is, maybe we're missing the real
message of this גמרא. Gemara
Right, yeah, it was מגלה טפח ומכסה טפח. megaleh tefach u'mechaseh tefach.
It's a phrase that's used there too, but this—and so you have
here מגלה טפח, megaleh tefach, טפח מתחתיו. tefach mitachtav. Okay, guys, you
beat me, like that's a
very—I'll read your—your פירוש peirush on this. Okay. Anyway, okay,
ועליו קערות וירק. ve'alev ka'arot v'yerek. Okay, and on it, let's read
the רשב״ם's Rashbam first way: on the exposed part is where you
put the dishes and the vegetables, וטבעתו מבחוץ. vetaba'ato mibachutz.
Now apparently they would suspend at least the table or the table
top, it would be removable, and they'd have a ring that they
would you know be attached to the table that you would use
to like hang it up against the wall when you weren't using
it. Guess if you have limited space. So that ring should be
if if like if everybody if all the guests are sitting on
this side, this is מבפנים, mibifnim, and the attendant is going on
the outside, so the ring should be pointing towards the outside. So
we'll see why in a minute. Who do you want the ring
to be possibly interfering with, the guests or the attendant? Okay, so
that's the question. So the גמרא Gemara says,
so the גמרא Gemara. interrupts this by saying והתניא טבעתו מבפנים, vehasanya
taba'ato mibifnim, we learned that the ring is on the inside? So
the גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא הא דאיכא ינוקא הא דליכא ינוקא.
lo kashya ha de'ika yanuka ha deleika yanuka. Oh, so parents with
small kids can identify. Do you have a baby or not a
baby? Okay, if you've got a baby, so then the baby is
going to play with the ring. So you want to keep the
ring away from the baby, you know he might get caught in
the ring or whatever, so you want to keep it away from
the baby, you put it on the outside, you know let the
attendant work to avoid it. But if you don't have a baby,
put it on the inside. It's easier for the seated guests to
avoid you know bumping into this ring than it is for the
attendant who's moving back and forth. Okay, ואיבעית אימא הא והא דליכא
ינוקא, ve'iba'is eima ha ve'ha deleika yanuka, there's no baby. ולא קשיא
הא דאיכא שמש הא דליכא שמש. velo kashya ha de'ika shamash ha
deleika shamash. Is there an attendant or not? If there's no attendant
you put it on the outside, if there is an attendant you
keep it on the inside, because the attendant is moving back and
forth, it's harder for him to avoid. ואיבעית אימא הא והא דאיכא
שמש, ve'iba'is eima ha ve'ha de'ika shamash, there is an attendant. ולא
קשיא הא ביממא הא בליליא, velo kashya ha b'imama ha b'leilya, or
day or night? In the daytime the attendant can avoid, and the
night time it's harder to avoid, you'll put it on the inside,
it's more of a problem for the attendant than for the guests.
Okay, anyway, that's the end of the table of a תלמיד חכם.
talmid chacham. ושל עם הארץ, veshel am ha'aretz, now what is the
table of an עם הארץ? am ha'aretz? דומה למדורה. domeh l'medurah. It's
like a, it's like a campfire. Okay, what's a, or you know
where you have the fire in the middle and you have all
the pots around it. Okay, so in that case, so if you
look at the רשב״ם: Rashbam: למדורה שמקפת קדרות והאש באמצע אף כאן
המפה והלחם באמצע. l'medurah shemukeves kederot ve'ha'esh be'emtza af kan hamapah ve'halechem
be'emtza. It's the flip of what we said before.
Okay, the, the, the cloth with all the food is on the
middle, is in the middle, והקערות מסביב, ve'haka'arot misaviv, and the dishes
are on the outside. So in that case, right, it's, wait, did
I get that right? אף כאן המפה והלחם באמצע. af kan hamapah
ve'halechem be'emtza.
Right, before we had it was two sides, the edges were covered
and the middle was open, and here it's the middle is covered
and the edges are open, and that's seen as being, I don't
know, more uncouth. Can't fully appreciate that, but it's more uncouth. Okay,
וקדרות מקיפות אותה. ukderot mekifot osah. Now, מיטה של תלמידי חכמים כיצד?
mitah shel talmidei chachamim keitzad? How about a bed of תלמידי חכמים?
talmidei chachamim? כל שאין תחתיה אלא סנדלים בימות החמה מנעלים בימות הגשמים.
kol she'ein tachteha ela sandalim biyemos hachamah minalim biyemos hageshamim. So something
that, you know, is you don't store a lot of stuff. According
to the גמרא anyway, if you store food under your bed, like
there's a רוח רעה ruach ra'ah that has, you know, that affects
it, you know, so you're not supposed to store food under your
bed. But anyway, it would be seen as like, you know, just
sort of like uncouth and sloppy to just, you know, throw everything
under your bed. So a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, he only has
the bare minimum that he stores under his bed: the shoes that
he is not wearing during that season. Somewhat ironically, okay, your sandals
apparently you wear in the winter. This is the way the רשב״ם
Rashbam says it because you're not afraid, in the winter things are
muddier and you don't want your shoes to get as muddy, so
you wear your sandals in the winter. So if it is the
summertime, you're storing your sandals under the bed. Okay, and your shoes
you wear in the summer. So if it's the wintertime, you're storing
your shoes under the bed. מנעלים בימות הגשמים. minalim biyemos hageshamim. Now,
I don't know, I would have thought the opposite. I would have
thought you wear your sandals in the summer and your shoes in
the winter, and you want your shoes right near your bed so
you can, you know, put on your shoes as soon as you
get up and get dressed. But whatever it is, he stores the
bare minimum, just one pair of shoes under his bed.
Are we sure that we know what these words mean? Maybe what
we think is sandals, a סנדל, sandal, is the closed shoe?
No, because he says the reason the סנדל sandal is because it's
not as, you know, you're there's not as much so you're not
as bothered if it gets filled with with mud. That's the way
the רשב״ם Rashbam explains it if you look at it. דרך לנעול
מנעלים בימות החמה וסנדלים בימות הגשמים בשביל הטיט. derech linol minalim biyemos
hachamah vesandalim biyemos hageshamim bishvil hatit.
Okay, you say you're not concerned that it's not,
I don't know, he says בשביל הטיט. bishvil hatit. That's how I
read it. I don't know, maybe I, there's other גמרות gemaros about
סנדלים. sandalim. I think the סנדלים sandalim are what they are now,
basic things with straps on them, yes?
I mean the way this is translated, if you want me to
share?
Yeah, what does it say?
So it's saying like any bed that has nothing stored beneath it
except hard leather shoes during the summer season.
Right, so he says סנדלים sandalim are hard leather. Right, that's what
I said, you're storing this
in the summer.
Right, but and what do they say מנעלים? minalim?
Storing the sandals in the winter. The sandals in the winter, right,
in the summer, right? And what does it mean? And soft leather
shoes during.
Oh, so maybe that's what Dov was saying. Maybe it's not just
the difference of whether it's straps or not, but a sandal has
a hard bottom, which makes it allow you to traverse the mud
better. Maybe that's what you were saying. Okay. So that could be.
It's not just a question about is it open or closed, but
you know, but how much is it good for traversing the mud.
That's helpful,
yeah. Okay, yeah. So עם הארץ Am Ha'aretz דומה לאוצר בלוס domeh
le'otzar balus somehow it's בלום balum but he's a... but the רשב"ם
says no, בלוס בסמ"ך, balus be-samech if you
look at it. אוצר, Otzar, yeah, בלוס
balus
בסמ"ך be-samech, כמו עיסה בלוסה kemo issa belusa במסכת שבת. be-masechet shabbat.
עיסה מעורבת ממינים הרבה. issa meurevet miminim harbe. But others do אוצר
בלום. otzar balum. What is a, it's a modern Israeli phrase? What
does it mean?
אוצר בלום. otzar balum.
It's like, ooh, there's like a treasure under their...
Oh, it's a good thing?
אוצר בלום? otzar balum? No, like, but I think here it would
be like a...
Yeah, so I think others have the גרסא girsa בלום, balum, that's
always the more natural thing. בלוס balus is a funny sounding word
in general. But anyway, he says it means like a בלאגן balagan
I guess, you know, a complete like, you know, mixture of crazy
things, okay, but it could be בלום balum also. Anyway, but the
point is עם הארץ Am Ha'aretz under his bed like, you know,
is going to be like, I don't know, there's got to be
a forest or something. Okay, you don't know what you're going to
find. All right, anyway, that was a nice interesting little, little digression.
We will pick up with רב בנאה Rav Banna and fascinating story
with רב בנאה Rav Banna come tomorrow. All right.
Oh, yeah, well that's true in the גמרא. The גמרא only recognizes
ימות הגשמים yemot hageshamim וימות החמה. ve-yemot hachamma.